<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Good English: or, Certain reasons pointing out the safest way of settlement in this kingdom; drawne from the nature of the aims and interests of the severall parties ingaged; and as the case now stands, this second day of May. 1648. A peece of serious observation, wherein the secrets of every party, as they stand in a probability of complyance, or opposition to His Majcsty [sic], are fully discovered.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85343</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1043</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E441_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202219</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204897</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862589</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862589</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114752</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85343)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114752)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 69:E441[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Good English: or, Certain reasons pointing out the safest way of settlement in this kingdom; drawne from the nature of the aims and interests of the severall parties ingaged; and as the case now stands, this second day of May. 1648. A peece of serious observation, wherein the secrets of every party, as they stand in a probability of complyance, or opposition to His Majcsty [sic], are fully discovered.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16, 13-24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeere 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 8".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Peace --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114752:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Good Engliſh: Or, Certain REASONS Pointing out the ſafeſt way of Settlement in this KINGDOM; Drawne from the nature of the <hi>Aims</hi> and <hi>Jntereſts</hi> of the ſeverall <hi>Parties</hi> ingaged; and as the Caſe now ſtands, this ſecond day of MAY. 1648.</p>
            <p>A Peece of ſerious obſervation, wherein the ſecrets of every <hi>Party,</hi> as they ſtand in a probability of Complyance, or Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> are fully diſcovered.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Seneca <hi>in</hi> Hercule <hi>fur:</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>—Proſperum ac foelix ſcelus,</l>
               <l>Virtus vecatur. Sontibus parent boni.</l>
               <l>Ius eſt in armis. Quaritur belli exitus,</l>
               <l>Non <hi>Cauſa:</hi> Nunc pereat omnis memoria,</l>
               <l>Et <hi>victor</hi> arma ponat, &amp; <hi>victum</hi> decet</l>
               <l>Deponere Odia.—</l>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Yeere 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:114752:2"/>
            <head>To the Lord Generall <hi>Fairfax.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis plaine <hi>Pamphlet</hi> was written partly for your ſake, and thoſe under your Command, that you may at length conſider what neceſſitie lies upon you, to ſecure your ſelves, and ſettle this <hi>Kingdom</hi> by an humble, honorable, and ſpeedy reconcilement with His <hi>Majeſty.</hi> Know this, that what I have written here, is written couragiouſly, and without <hi>reſpect of Perſons:</hi> And becauſe the truth of it is of ſo univerſall concernment, that it requires the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſall of all ſores of men within the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> I have ſent it abroad in a more homely <hi>ſtile</hi> than uſuall, that it may find entertainment in the meaneſt <hi>capacities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reaſon that induced me to make this <hi>Addreſſe</hi> unto your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> is, becauſe it aimes principally at your <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt,</hi> who are the <hi>Captaine</hi> of that <hi>Army,</hi> which hitherto hath lengthened our miſeries by <hi>breach of Faith</hi> with the <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Kingdom:</hi> And though I am apt to believe (as well as others) that you had the leaſt ſhare in that odious and abominable <hi>deſigne</hi> of impriſoning our <hi>Soveraigne;</hi> yet the world knowes you may (if you pleaſe) and is almoſt perſwaded you will, become the happy inſtrument of his <hi>deliverance.</hi> It is the humor of our owne and other <hi>Nations</hi> to talke, as if the Military Affaires were ſwayed wholly by your <hi>Lievtenant-Generall.</hi> I cannot tell how farre he and his potent <hi>Party</hi> may have wrought upon you heretofore by ſpecious Arguments, or preſumed to act many <hi>Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies</hi> at ſuch a time when you could not ſafely oppoſe them; but this I aſſuredly know, that they are all laid upon your <hi>ſcore,</hi> and that now is the time wherein you may <hi>quit
<pb facs="tcp:114752:2"/>ſcores,</hi> and become <hi>your ſelfe,</hi> who of your ſelfe (I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident) are indued with ſuch excellent principles of <hi>honor, reaſon,</hi> and <hi>reſolution,</hi> that you cannot but doe like your <hi>ſelfe,</hi> having ſo faire an <hi>oportunity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is it may opinion only, but the hope and perſwaſion of many <hi>gallant</hi> men, which yet retaine ſome thoughts of <hi>honor</hi> concerning you, for your <hi>bravery</hi> and <hi>civility</hi> in your <hi>Conqueſts.</hi> Oh, let not the memory of them (which may be applauded in <hi>after-times,</hi> though not for the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> yet for the gallant performance) be obliterated by ſiniſter and prodigious undertakings! Remember that you ſtand in the rank of <hi>Nobility,</hi> and may tranſmit this <hi>honor</hi> with the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of greater, unto your <hi>Poſterity;</hi> acquit then your ſelf nobly, and let not the <hi>fountain</hi> from whence you derived your <hi>honor,</hi> be thus prophaned, and vilified by the very <hi>filth</hi> of the <hi>people.</hi> Conſider the miſeries that muſt fall upon your <hi>Country,</hi> by an Army of hungry <hi>Strangers</hi> now ready to invade us: Imagine that the eyes of the <hi>Nation</hi> are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, as one that may prevent all, or at leaſt ſhorten their abode here, by uniting with his <hi>Majeſtie.</hi> Baniſh that accurſed Principle of <hi>not truſting an injured Prince,</hi> which becomes none but implacable and incorrigible <hi>Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</hi> See that ſuch <hi>Terms</hi> be propounded unto him, that may not claſh either with his <hi>Conſcience</hi> or <hi>Honor,</hi> that it may appear unto all men, you deſire <hi>Peace</hi> at his hands, who is the moſt <hi>peaceable, pious, gracious</hi> Prince living. But if you entertain other <hi>Counſells,</hi> know that you will be look'd on by the <hi>people,</hi> as the <hi>cauſe</hi> of all thoſe <hi>deſolations</hi> which ſhall befall them; and the time of <hi>Revenge</hi> will come, (from above) wherein you ſhall with <hi>ſorrow,</hi> confeſſe your neglect of this honeſt <hi>Advice,</hi> given from a <hi>private</hi> hand, that would thinke it an <hi>honor</hi> to kiſſe yours, if your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> pleaſe firſt to kiſſe <hi>Majeſtie's,</hi> upon <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>honorable</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:114752:3"/>
            <head>Good Engliſh: OR, Certaine Reaſons pointing out the ſafeſt way of ſettlement in this Kingdome.</head>
            <head type="sub">Drawne from the nature of the <hi>aimes,</hi> and <hi>Intereſts</hi> of the ſeverall <hi>parties</hi> ingaged; and as the caſe now ſtands, this ſecond day of <hi>May,</hi> 1648.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>Firſt, by reaſons drawne from the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Royall Epiſcopall</hi> Party.</head>
               <p>HIs <hi>Majeſty</hi> muſt owe the ruine of his <hi>affaires,</hi> to the <hi>emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> of his <hi>Superior Officers,</hi> and the ſecurity and intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance of the <hi>Inferiour.</hi> The <hi>Houſes</hi> (though <hi>Conquerors</hi>) muſt attribute the great deficiency and inſtability of their <hi>affaires,</hi> to <hi>private Intereſt</hi> and <hi>Faction;</hi> the very <hi>Twins</hi> of all <hi>popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar</hi> ingagements.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Factions</hi> are divided into theſe two notions, <hi>Preſbyterian,</hi> and <hi>Independent;</hi> both of them <hi>humours</hi> inconſiſtent with the true temper of the <hi>Body Politique</hi> of <hi>England:</hi> And they may fitly be compared unto two <hi>poyſons</hi> of a contrary quality, which maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a <hi>war</hi> within the <hi>Body naturall,</hi> vex it with many dire <hi>ſymptoms,</hi> to the diſturbance of the whole <hi>Oeconomy;</hi> and never reſt, till being evacuated by ſome ſtrong <hi>Purger,</hi> or elſe tired out by <hi>re-action,</hi> the ſtrife ends: And ſo <hi>nature</hi> recovering her firſt vigor, reduces the <hi>Body</hi> into its former <hi>ſtate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Such as the event in this caſe, is in the body of man, the like may we expect at length, to be the iſſue of theſe <hi>counter-workings</hi> of the two venemous <hi>Factions,</hi> within the bowells of this Land. For, it muſt needs be, either that in long running they will tire out each other; or elſe the <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> of the people not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to beare them any longer, they may at laſt be vomited out of the <hi>Nation.</hi> But rather than the <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſhould be tormented, in expectation of the iſſue of ſo pernicious a <hi>Conflict</hi> betwixt thoſe two <hi>extremes,</hi> it were convenient, his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> as a <hi>third party,</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:114752:3"/>ſhould ſpeedily clap in, to ballance the one againſt the other, or elſe conquer both; there being but theſe two wayes to end the <hi>Controverſie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Touching the <hi>Conqueſt</hi> of both (though it be the fartheſt way about) he hath one maine <hi>advantage</hi> which may carry him through with the <hi>work;</hi> and that is the large <hi>Empire</hi> which he yet holds in the hearts of his people, which is exceedingly confirmed and dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly augmented, by reaſon of thoſe intolerable burthens that lie upon them; the ſenſe whereof makes them looke upon the <hi>King,</hi> as their companion in miſery, and on the two <hi>Factions,</hi> as the <hi>Fountaines</hi> from whence all theſe <hi>evills</hi> flow.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Foraine aids,</hi> it is confeſſed, the Affairs of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> are at this time ſo diſpoſed, and every <hi>Potentate</hi> ſo exhauſted, or inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, that ſome want <hi>leiſure;</hi> others, ability to aſſiſt him: And o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that have both <hi>ability,</hi> and <hi>leiſure,</hi> yet refraine out of ſome particular <hi>Reaſons of State.</hi> The <hi>Spaniard</hi> hath his hands full every way, and hath more cauſe to ſeeke to repaire himſelfe, than aſſiſt others: The <hi>French</hi> are his Invaders; the <hi>Portugalls,</hi> Revolters; and the <hi>Neapolitans,</hi> Rebells.</p>
               <p>The <hi>French</hi> are buſie in maintaining what they have gotten, and ſeeking after more: But if they were at leiſure, little might be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from them, unleſſe it were to foment our <hi>differences,</hi> and as they firſt helped to <hi>unſettle</hi> us, ſo ſtill to keep us from ſetling, that <hi>England</hi> (which is the ballancing power of <hi>Europe,</hi> and her King <hi>Arbiter orbis Christiani,</hi> the Arbitrator in all differences of <hi>Chriſtendome</hi>) being broken by her owne ſtrength at home, might have none to ſpend abroad, to hinder that prodigious <hi>deſign,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the late ſucceſſes of the <hi>French</hi> have heightned them to become <hi>Rivalls</hi> and <hi>Competitors</hi> with the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> for an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Denmark</hi> hath enough to do in repairing thoſe ruines, which were brought on them by the late <hi>Swediſh</hi> Incurſions.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Hollanders</hi> eſteem it a ſafe way to conform themſelves e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to the <hi>prevailing</hi> party in <hi>England,</hi> ſeeing they have a great part of their livelyhood by Indulgence from the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation: More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, though at firſt they eſteemed the <hi>Match</hi> of the Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range</hi> with the eldeſt daughter of <hi>England,</hi> as a matter of much honour; yet now they look upon it as a buſineſſe that in time may prove of ill conſequence; fearing ſo great an alliance might diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the <hi>Prince</hi> to aſpire, and eſtabliſh a greater <hi>Interest</hi> of his own, than is meet for a Member of a <hi>Republike,</hi> if <hi>Monarchy</hi> were at its
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114752:4"/>height againe in <hi>England.</hi> And, further many among the <hi>Dutch,</hi> ſuppoſing that the <hi>Grandees</hi> here aime at the ſame forme of <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> with themſelves, doe flatter themſelves in conceit, that ſuch a <hi>neighbourhood</hi> would be willing to admit of a nearer friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and complication of <hi>Intereſts,</hi> than can be hoped for from a <hi>Monarchy,</hi> though there be farre more reaſon to ſuſpect the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
               <p>So that wee ſee how little his <hi>Majeſty</hi> may expect from any of his <hi>Neighbors:</hi> And truly, it is no ſmall part of our happineſſe in the midſt of theſe <hi>diſtractions,</hi> that we have had, and are like to have, ſo little of their Company.</p>
               <p>The hopes then of his <hi>Majeſties</hi> reſtitution being wholly founded upon the affections of his <hi>People,</hi> and bounded within his owne <hi>Dominions,</hi> let us take a view of each within their <hi>ſtation.</hi> The <hi>Scots</hi> ſeem to bee divided among themſelves; ſome pretend abſolutely for his <hi>Majeſty;</hi> others, only upon condition of ſigning the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> &amp;c. In <hi>Ireland</hi> a <hi>Ceſſation</hi> will open a way for ſupplies out of that <hi>Kingdome.</hi> In <hi>Wales,</hi> they are in arms already for his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and all the Royall Party in <hi>England</hi> wait but for an <hi>Oportunity</hi> in the ſame way, to free themſelves from their preſent vaſſalage, under the power of the <hi>Independent</hi> party in the <hi>Houſes;</hi> wherein likewiſe the <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> party are as much concerned as any, ſeeing the other of <hi>Brethren,</hi> are become their bitter <hi>enemies,</hi> and would ſhew them as little courteſie, as others, were it not to ſtop the mouthes of their <hi>leading men</hi> at home, and in hope to work upon the prime <hi>Preſbyters</hi> in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What the <hi>Refult</hi> of the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> reſolutions will be, is yet not certainly knowne. If the <hi>pretending royall party</hi> there carry an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement <hi>ſimply</hi> for the <hi>King,</hi> no doubt but the <hi>Royalliſts</hi> here joyning with them, they may finiſh the <hi>work</hi> by ſubduing both the <hi>Factions:</hi> But if they bring in a <hi>mixt</hi> Ingagement, for the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Covenant</hi> (which we have great cauſe to fear,) I conceive the <hi>Royalliſts</hi> ought not to joyne with them, but to expect and indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour a Cloſe with the <hi>Independent</hi> party; who will be forced for their owne ſafety, to wave their <hi>high-flowne Reſolutions,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>think themſelves of a <hi>Complyance</hi> with his <hi>Majeſty;</hi> which ought rather to be ſought after and imbraced (as leſſe dangerous to the <hi>royall Prerogative</hi>) than a cloſe with the <hi>Preſbyterian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Touching the probabilitv and conveniency of a <hi>Complyance</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt his <hi>Majesty</hi> and the <hi>Independent</hi> party, in caſe the <hi>Scots</hi> ingage for <hi>Presbyterie,</hi> I ſhall endeavour to fortifie my opinion by unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114752:4"/>
                  <hi>Reaſons:</hi> But firſt give me leave to manifeſt the great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of cloſing with the <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> Party, though accompanied with never ſo many ſpecious pretences.</p>
               <p>That a <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Ingaging for <hi>the Covenant</hi> (reſolved on, as it ſeems) will be clearly deſtructive to <hi>Monarchicall Intereſt,</hi> I ſhall prove in ſeverall particulars. Firſt, becauſe they aim thereby at the introduction of <hi>Preſbyterie,</hi> and the over-turning of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> the maine pillar of <hi>Monarchy,</hi> as it hath ever been eſteemed in this <hi>Nation.</hi> And therefore it was, that all the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> from time to time, have ſo willingly ſworne, to <hi>grant and to preſerve unto the</hi> Biſhops, <hi>and to the Churches commited to their Charge, all Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call privileges, and due Law and Juſtice, and to protect and defend them &amp;c.</hi> And King <hi>JAMES,</hi> who had long experience of the ſad effects of the alteration of that Government in the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> was ſo fully convinced of the neare relation betwixt <hi>Epiſcopacie</hi> and <hi>Monarchy,</hi> that hee left this for a ſure <hi>Aphoriſm</hi> to his <hi>Poſterity,</hi> No BISHOP No KING. For, it having been of ſo long continuance here, and deeply rooted in the <hi>Lawes</hi> of this Kingdom, it muſt needs be that a change in the one, will work an alteration in the other.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The Truth hereof was ſo well knowne to the <hi>Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>builders</hi> of this <hi>Reformation,</hi> whoſe <hi>Aime</hi> appears now to have been <hi>ab origine</hi> (how contrary ſoever their <hi>Pretences</hi> were) for an alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the <hi>civill</hi> government; that they firſt began their work with pulling downe of <hi>Epiſcopacie,</hi> that in the ruines thereof they might lay the foundation of their new <hi>deſigne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, It is very apparent of what ill conſequence, the extirpation of <hi>Epiſcopacie</hi> will be to his Majeſty, ſeeing it is a meanes to clip the <hi>Crowne</hi> of a very conſiderable part of its <hi>Revenues,</hi> which by the Lawes of the Land, are annexed thereunto; as the <hi>collation</hi> of <hi>Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks</hi> and <hi>Deaneries;</hi> the <hi>firſt fruits</hi> and profits of their Lands and Revenues, during their vacancies; the <hi>firſt fruits</hi> and <hi>yearly Tenths</hi> out of all <hi>Eccleſiasticall Promotions;</hi> and ſundry other privileges, profits, and emoluments, ariſing out of the <hi>State Eccleſiaſticall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, to ingage for <hi>Preſbytery,</hi> is to indeavour the intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing of a <hi>Democraticall</hi> form of Government, which is directly incompatible with a <hi>Monarchy;</hi> and as it cannot ſtand with the power of our <hi>government,</hi> ſo it withſtands the Honour of our <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verner,</hi> debaſing the Majeſty of <hi>Monarchy</hi> into a <hi>popular parity,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect of his moſt <hi>ſacred Perſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, by ingaging for <hi>Preſbyterie,</hi> they labor to erect a power in the State <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> diſtinct from that of the Civill: for it is a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114752:5"/>
                  <hi>Maxim</hi> among all <hi>Preſbyters,</hi> and we find it pleaded for at large in the <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of Faith agreed upon by the Aſſembly at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> (which as yet the <hi>Houſes</hi> have been more wiſe than to confirme) that <hi>there ought to be a power in the Church diſtinct from that of the Civill:</hi> which <hi>Tenet</hi> of <hi>diſtinction</hi> muſt bee the ſame in effect with that of the Church of <hi>Rome's</hi> ſupremacy; ſeeing, thoſe which now plead for a power without the <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill,</hi> will not bee long before they arrive to ſuch a height of preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, as to act above it, or againſt it, in purſuance of their own <hi>deſignes.</hi> It will be a hard matter to keep ſuch a <hi>Governmeut</hi> within its limits, in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> and therefore with much difficulty will it ſubmit to bee governed by a free <hi>Monarchy;</hi> eſpecially a <hi>Democracie</hi> of this new Nature, which makes the ſame Perſons <hi>civill</hi> Subjects, and <hi>eccleſiaſticall</hi> Superiors.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, it is not like that <hi>Preſbyterie</hi> ſhould prove the <hi>Mother</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> conſidering that ſhee was born the Daughter of <hi>ſedition,</hi> and hath ever ſince been nurſed up by <hi>Tumults</hi> and <hi>Rebellion.</hi> For, <hi>Geneva</hi> was the Land of her <hi>Nativity,</hi> where M. <hi>Calvin</hi> was her Father; and no doubt, conſidering the ſtate of thoſe Affairs &amp; conditions of men, among whom hee was converſant, it was a commendable invention, and very neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for bridling the tumultuous Humors in a <hi>free City;</hi> And ſo far we may beleeve hee intended it, yeelding to a <hi>popular Parity,</hi> and not as an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall perpetuall form of government for all <hi>reformed Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seventhly, it is obſervable, that this ill <hi>weed</hi> hath growne in none but <hi>popular</hi> gardens, in ſome parts of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> till ſome ſeditious <hi>Planters</hi> and <hi>Waterers,</hi> cauſed it to ſpring up among the <hi>Thistles</hi> of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> And of what ſad conſequence it hath proved to <hi>Monarchicall</hi> government in that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> let the world judge: For, the Foundation of it was laid in the ruine of our King's <hi>Grandmother,</hi> and the ſuperſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture continued, to the perpetuall diſcontent and vexation of his <hi>Father,</hi> till hee was moſt happily poſſeſſed of the Crown of <hi>England;</hi> Nor could hee have been ſecure here, but that by his great wiſedom hee ſtaved it off: And now at length, the <hi>Faction</hi> having with great ſubtilty gotten foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in this Kingdom, wee ſee at this day, how faire a ſtroke it hath given toward the ruine of his Son, our moſt gracious <hi>Soveraigne,</hi> and his whole <hi>Poſterity.</hi> For, though he languiſh now under the power of the other <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> yet the firſt <hi>deſigne</hi> of war was laid in and by <hi>Preſbyterie,</hi> and his <hi>Majesty</hi> ſuffered Reſtraint firſt under the <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> power; whoſe au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacious carriage toward his Perſon, in hope to tire him out of his noble principles, taught others ſo much impudence, as to endeavour to ſerve their ends upon him, by a <hi>cloſe impriſonment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Eightly, ſeeing His Majeſty is reſolved to keep ſo cloſe to his <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,</hi> (as is well knowne unto all the world) that he will never yeeld
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114752:5"/>to the extirpation of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> what then may we expect from a <hi>Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall</hi> Ingagement, but that when they have made uſe of the <hi>King's Name</hi> to quell the <hi>Independent Faction,</hi> as the <hi>Independent</hi> did to quell them, they will upon his <hi>Majeſties</hi> refuſall of their demands, (which he hath ever declared to be againſt his <hi>conſcience</hi> and <hi>honor</hi>) returne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to their old <hi>vomi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and either keep his <hi>Majeſty</hi> in the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition he now is, or worſe, till they can ſettle themſelves and their pernicious <hi>Preſbytery,</hi> paſt all hope of remedy? And then (perhaps) he ſhall be called out of priſon to be manacled in his <hi>Throne,</hi> as his Father was in <hi>Scotland,</hi> who could never act, but when they pleaſed to let him; and then onely according to their <hi>Directory</hi> of <hi>Kirk</hi> and <hi>State.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From hence (I conceive) we may poſitively and plainely affirme, that the Iſſue of a <hi>Preſbyterian Ingagement</hi> (though uſher'd in with never ſo many ſpecious pretences for his <hi>Majesty</hi>) will be utterly deſtructive to the <hi>Royall Interest</hi> of this Kingdom: And therefore if the <hi>Scots</hi> come in upon ſuch <hi>termes,</hi> the <hi>Royall Party</hi> ought not to ingage with them, nor to countenance them, but to expect, and indeavour a <hi>Complyance</hi> with the <hi>Independent,</hi> as I ſhall further illuſtrate by reaſon.</p>
               <p>Firſt, though ſome may object that it cannot ſtand with his <hi>Majeſties</hi> Honor to comply with thoſe, that have already abuſed his inclination in that particular: yet if they duly conſider, what urgencie lies at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent upon his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and how little hope there is of any better way of reſtitution, they may conceive it far more politique to obey <hi>neceſſity,</hi> than ſtand upon nice <hi>Punctillo's</hi> of honor; which I muſt confeſſe a Prince in proſperity ought to have regard unto, <hi>ad conſervandam Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatem Imperii;</hi> but if once he be trampled under the feet of <hi>fortune,</hi> ceremonious reſpects muſt be laid aſide, to Court the firſt <hi>Oportunity,</hi> which reaſon ſhall point out, for a <hi>deliverance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, if it be objected, that the <hi>Independent</hi> party have a deſigne for <hi>alteration</hi> of government, I anſwer, ſo I believe the Presbyters have too; onely here is all the difference betwixt them, that the <hi>Independents</hi> would not have a <hi>King</hi> ſo much as in <hi>Name,</hi> the <hi>Scots</hi> Presbyters would have no more but the Name of a <hi>King:</hi> The one aimes downright at an <hi>Aristocraticall</hi> forme of Government; the other pretends to maintain <hi>Monarchicall</hi> Government, yet actually deſtroyes the very Principles of <hi>Monarchy.</hi> And as for the <hi>Independent,</hi> it is cleare by their impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>King,</hi> their declaring againſt him, and to ſettle the Kingdom without him, that they have had, and ſtill may continue a <hi>deſigne</hi> to change the <hi>Kingly</hi> Government, and (in plaine termes) declare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>Free Sates,</hi> if by any meanes they can allay the <hi>Scots:</hi> But there being little hopes of that, we may gueſſe how unable they are to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine their Station, having over-ſtrained the ſinews of the <hi>City,</hi> and the heart-ſtrings, of the Country; and ſo it is probable they will ſcarce be ſo hardy as to venture, to ſtand upon their ſingle leggs, againſt the ſtreame
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114752:6"/>of a generall diſ-affection at home, and an invaſion by their <hi>oppoſite Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> from abroad; but may, when there is no hope of carrying on their deſigne any longer that way, retreat with <hi>moderation</hi> toward His <hi>Majeſty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, ſeeing it is dangerous, in caſe the <hi>Scots</hi> come in for <hi>Preſbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> that the <hi>Royall</hi> party ſhould ingage with them, it is all the reaſon in the world they ſhould with ſpeed indeavour an <hi>Agreement</hi> with the <hi>Independent:</hi> For, if <hi>Preſbytery</hi> receive a foile from the <hi>Independents,</hi> then they will undoubtedly be heightned with confidence to proſecute their deſigne againſt <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and (perhaps) in time attaine ſo much pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as to eſtabliſh themſelves: And on the other ſide, if <hi>Independency</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a foile from the <hi>Preſbyters,</hi> then Presbyteriall Government will uſurp over <hi>Monarchy;</hi> both which inconveniencies will be prevented by a timely cloſe with the <hi>Independent.</hi> For, there is no other way to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſh his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> unleſſe we ſuppoſe his <hi>Party</hi> able to carry it by force of Armes againſt both the <hi>Factions:</hi> which (if it were poſſible) cannot be effected without length of time, extreme difficulty, and the ſad conſequences of a <hi>Second War.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, an Agreement with the <hi>Independent</hi> is the only way to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a <hi>Second war.</hi> For, They being Poſſeſſed of all, or moſt of the places of ſtrength in this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and back't beſides with an <hi>Army,</hi> it muſt needs bee, that an Ingaging againſt them, cannot be carried on to a <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> but through a <hi>Sea</hi> of <hi>Bloud,</hi> and a generall <hi>devaſtation:</hi> whereas an <hi>union</hi> betwixt them and his <hi>Majesty,</hi> contracted upon mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, juſt, and equitable grounds, in relation to his <hi>Majesties</hi> Intereſts and due <hi>Rights,</hi> and the People's <hi>Birthright,</hi> will bee a meanes not only to prevent the afore-ſaid <hi>Miſcheife;</hi> but ſo quell the <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> Party in <hi>England,</hi> that they ſhall not bee able to countenance any <hi>Scotiſh</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes: And ſo, if the <hi>Scots</hi> do attempt an <hi>Invaſion</hi> upon any <hi>Pretence</hi> whatſoever, the <hi>Warr</hi> will bee brought home to their owne dores.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, ſeeing there is a neceſſity of ſome <hi>form,</hi> it is probable the <hi>Complyance</hi> will extend ſo far, as to let us have <hi>Biſhops</hi> again. And there is ſo much the more hope, in regard the <hi>Independents</hi> have not yet abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely agreed to the ſettling of any one particular way of <hi>Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment;</hi> the execution of all Ordinances hitherto in relation to <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterie,</hi> being permitted merely out of <hi>policie</hi> to pacifie that <hi>Faction</hi> for a time, and not out of any reſpect to the <hi>Government</hi> it ſelfe; which they looke upon as far more deſtructive to liberty, and which brings in ten thouſand ſuch <hi>Inconveniences</hi> and <hi>Preſſures,</hi> as are not incident in a <hi>well-regulated Epiſcopacy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixthly, if it bee objected, that there is little hope of the <hi>Independents</hi> yielding to <hi>Biſhops,</hi> ſeeing they have been as deeply ingaged in the <hi>ſale</hi> of their <hi>Lands,</hi> as ever <hi>Presbyters</hi> were; it muſt bee conſidered, that what they have done in this kind of <hi>Robbery,</hi> was only (as their <hi>elder Brethren</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:114752:6"/>the <hi>Preſbyters,</hi> gave them example) in order to their <hi>Deſigne</hi> for <hi>alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> of <hi>Government;</hi> which now being forced to quit (as anon I ſhall prove) by <hi>invincible</hi> neceſſity, ſome other waies may and muſt bee taken for the ſatisfaction of the ſouldiery than by the Goods of the <hi>Church.</hi> And then likewiſe it will bee no hard matter to make our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſing <hi>Cormorants,</hi> to vomit up all their ſweet <hi>Sacrilegious Morſels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, though moſt of the <hi>Royall Party</hi> are rendred wholly averſe to a <hi>Cloſe</hi> with the <hi>Independent</hi> Party, as Perſons not to bee dealt with, by reaſon of their groſſe <hi>Juglings</hi> with his <hi>Majeſty;</hi> yet give me leave to ſay, that as their <hi>Ambition, avarice</hi> and <hi>over-weening confidence,</hi> were the cauſes of their declining thoſe faire <hi>Propoſals</hi> and <hi>Pretences</hi> of their firſt <hi>Ingagement,</hi> ſuppoſing that then they had an <hi>Oportunity</hi> to doe what they pleaſed; ſo now being deceived in their expectations, and having found by experience, that they are not able to go through with their <hi>Deſigne;</hi> and it being cleare alſo (as I ſhall manifeſt) that they have no hope of <hi>Safety,</hi> or, continuance in this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> but by a <hi>Cordiall Cloſe</hi> with his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> wee have little or no Cauſe to feare a ſecond <hi>Baffle</hi> upon <hi>ſophiſticall</hi> Pretences, in time to come; eſpecially if his <hi>Majestie's</hi> wiſdom bee laid in the <hi>Balance</hi> with their <hi>Neceſſity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And ſo for theſe</hi> Reaſons I <hi>conceive, we may boldly affirm; that as</hi> the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Party <hi>ought by no meanes to admit of an</hi> Ingagement <hi>with, or for Presbyterte</hi> (<hi>though ſet on foot with the faireſt</hi> Pretences:) <hi>ſo their true</hi> Intereſt <hi>at preſent is to ſeek, and imbrace a timely diſcreet</hi> Complyance <hi>with that Party</hi> Paramount <hi>of this Kingdom, which they call</hi> Independent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>II. Reaſons</hi> drawn from the Interest of the ruling <hi>Independent</hi> Party.</head>
               <p>WHen firſt his <hi>Majeſty</hi> became a Priſoner to the <hi>Independent</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the <hi>Kingdom</hi> (as well as himſelfe) was filled with great hope of ſuch a mutuall <hi>Complyance</hi> betwixt him and them, as might uſher in the long-deſired <hi>ſettlement</hi> of this diſtracted <hi>Nation:</hi> Our expectations in this particular were exceedingly heightned by the many ſpecious <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, Repreſentations,</hi> and <hi>Propoſalls,</hi> ſent abroad from the <hi>Army;</hi> which promiſed much, in relation to the <hi>juſt Rights</hi> of his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and his <hi>Royall Posterity,</hi> and the true ſatisfaction of all <hi>Intereſts,</hi> as well as their owne; together with many glorious <hi>pretences</hi> of <hi>moderation</hi> toward thoſe of the <hi>Royall Party,</hi> and the eaſing of all <hi>burthens</hi> which lay upon the <hi>Subject.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe were indeed moſt rich and glorious <hi>pretences:</hi> And without controverſie this way of <hi>Complyance</hi> was at that time their true <hi>Inetereſt,</hi> and had they proſecuted it according to their <hi>Propoſalls,</hi> they had laid a ſtable <hi>foundation</hi> of their owne and the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> future happineſſe. But they, forſaking the true paths which led to <hi>Peace,</hi> immediately fell a wandring from theſe <hi>Principles</hi> in ſuch an <hi>erroneous</hi> courſe, that as the <hi>wiſer</hi> ſort of men fore-ſaw, ſo themſelves now begin to feare and feele,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114752:7"/>the <hi>fatall conſequences</hi> of their wretched <hi>diſſimulation;</hi> which is like to bring no leſſe <hi>ſorrow</hi> upon the <hi>Ring-leaders</hi> of that <hi>Faction,</hi> than it hath done already upon their <hi>Fellow-Subjects,</hi> and their <hi>Soveraigne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Reaſons which induced them to deale ſo perfidiouſly with his <hi>Majesty,</hi> were (no doubt, as I mentioned before) <hi>Ambition</hi> and <hi>Avarice;</hi> as hath ſince appeared by their ſeizing all places of <hi>profit,</hi> in the hands of themſelves, and their <hi>Kindred,</hi> and <hi>Creatures:</hi> And alſo by their groſſe and palpable <hi>deſignings</hi> for a change of <hi>Monarchicall</hi> Government. Upon a <hi>Change</hi> (for certain) they were all reſolved; but what new <hi>form</hi> to introduce in the place of it, was unknowne, and is as yet at this day, even to the principall among themſelves. For, as the <hi>Cauſe</hi> at firſt was ſplit into the two <hi>Factions</hi> of <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> and <hi>Independent;</hi> ſo this of <hi>Independency</hi> is ſub-divided into that Party which is commonly called <hi>Independent,</hi> and the other <hi>Party,</hi> moſt rightly called <hi>Levellers.</hi> The <hi>Grandees</hi> of that Party commonly called <hi>Independent,</hi> are ſome of the <hi>ſuperior Officers</hi> of the Army, and <hi>Members</hi> of either <hi>Houſe;</hi> the greateſt part of whom are viſible in the <hi>State-Committee</hi> at <hi>Derby</hi>-houſe: And though when his <hi>Majesty</hi> was firſt impriſoned, they then pretended, and would ſtill ſeem, to be one in deſigne with the <hi>Levellers,</hi> yet time hath manifeſted their <hi>aim</hi> to be at an <hi>Ariſtocraticall</hi> Form of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and (in plaine terms) to declare themſelves and their ſelect <hi>Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates</hi> FREE STATES.</p>
               <p>The other Party called <hi>Levellers,</hi> conſiſt onely of ſome <hi>Colonells</hi> and Commanders of Inferiour Rank in the <hi>Army,</hi> with whom are joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſome few <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Commons</hi> Houſe, and a confuſed <hi>Rabble</hi> of <hi>Sectaries</hi> in the <hi>Army, City,</hi> and <hi>Suburbs,</hi> and ſome parts of the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</hi> Their aime is at a <hi>Democraticall</hi> form of Government; inveſting the power wholly in the <hi>people:</hi> So that this wild Faction <hi>ex profeſſo,</hi> are enemies alike both to <hi>Monarchy</hi> and <hi>Optimacy,</hi> and will be governed neither by <hi>Kings,</hi> nor <hi>States.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence it was, that as ſoon as his <hi>Majesty</hi> was juggled away into the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> the <hi>ſuperior Officers,</hi> in order to their <hi>State-deſigne,</hi> ſaw there was a neceſſity of cruſhing the <hi>Levellers</hi> Party, after that they had ſerved their ends upon them, by drawing them into an ingaging upon the ſame pretended common <hi>Principles</hi> with themſelves. And therefore their firſt work was with all ſpeed to diſſipate the <hi>Councell</hi> of the Army, contrary to their firſt <hi>ingagement,</hi> and ſurprize them with a new <hi>ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> at <hi>Ware,</hi> deſtructive to the other at <hi>New-Market;</hi> whereinto the Souldiery were partly allured by <hi>ſoothings,</hi> and partly driven by <hi>terror,</hi> one of their fellow-ſouldiers being condemned for reſiſtance, by a <hi>Councell</hi> of Warre, and ſhot to death before their faces at the generall <hi>Rendezvous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Levellers</hi> Party being thus quell'd, there remained yet one <hi>Rub</hi> more in the way to this <hi>new</hi> STATE, and that was the <hi>Preſbyter</hi> Party:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:114752:7"/>As for the <hi>Royall</hi> Party, they were cruſhed alreadie, undone for want of their Eſtates, or by unmeaſurable <hi>Compoſitions</hi> to regain them, and their <hi>King</hi> reduced to a forlorn deſpicable condition of <hi>impriſonment,</hi> ſo that it was preſumed, he or they could have little hope, or meanes to revive againe: There remained then onely the <hi>Gulph</hi> of <hi>Preſbytery</hi> to ſaile through to their deſired <hi>Haven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They knew very well, that the Breaſts of the <hi>Preſbyterians</hi> boiled high with indignation and revenge againſt them, as their contrary <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> that had over-awed and ſubdued them by force and ſubtilty, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come poſſeſſors of what was once theirs, and ſhare in the glory of that <hi>new Government,</hi> which had been deſigned, and devoured in hope long before, by the <hi>Preſbyters:</hi> Therefore the <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> being a potent <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> by reaſon of the great <hi>interest</hi> it hath in the City of <hi>London,</hi> and their neare union with <hi>Scotland,</hi> and indeed the major <hi>Party</hi> in the <hi>Houſe</hi> on their ſide, if it were not <hi>over-awed;</hi> they judged it neceſſary to bethinke themſelves of ſome way to pacifie the <hi>Presbyterians.</hi> To this end they firſt fell to bribing of the grand <hi>Presbyterian-ſticklers</hi> in the <hi>Houſe,</hi> either with ſums of money in recompence of pretended <hi>loſſes,</hi> or of <hi>Arreares,</hi> or elſe with great <hi>Offices,</hi> which ſtaid their ſtomacks, and held the reſt of the <hi>Presbyters</hi> in ſuſpence, upon hope of the like in time according to their merits.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Scots,</hi> it was with high confidence preſumed, that they might bee taken off upon good valuable Conſiderations; wherein the <hi>aſpiring States</hi> have not been wanting by prodigious <hi>Offers,</hi> though all will not prevaile.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>City,</hi> if after the pacifying of the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> in the <hi>Houſe,</hi> they could likewiſe have made ſure of the <hi>Scots</hi> connivence, the <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian</hi> Party of <hi>Londoners</hi> muſt have fallen of courſe, as not able to ſtand out by themſelves.</p>
               <p>And ſo here now we have a full view of the <hi>Deſigne</hi> of the preſent <hi>ruling Independent</hi> Party: For, if after they had cruſhed the <hi>Levellers,</hi> they could by any meanes have made ſure work with the <hi>Presbyters</hi> at home and in <hi>Scotland,</hi> then there had been nothing betwixt them and home, but his <hi>Majeſty</hi> and his <hi>posterity,</hi> who being all of them at their Diſpoſition and power, beſides the <hi>Prince,</hi> and hee not likely to receive much comfort by ſuccour from <hi>foraine</hi> Parts, I leave the world to judge, what ſhould have been the conſequence of their wretched deſigne.</p>
               <p>But ſince it appeares (and themſelves are now perſwaded in their hearts,) that God hath otherwiſe determined concerning his ſacred <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and his numerous flouriſhing <hi>poſterity;</hi> ſeeing their laſt hopes faile them, and they begin to languiſh in the <hi>Cloſe</hi> of their <hi>Work,</hi> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it is high time to <hi>retreat,</hi> before the <hi>Dore</hi> be bolted againſt all hope of <hi>Pacification;</hi> and it muſt needs bee their true <hi>Intereſt,</hi> to recall his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> to let him <hi>Treat</hi> with freedom, and bethink themſelves of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114752:8"/>ſome neceſſary expedients toward an honorable, equall, and perfect <hi>reconciliation;</hi> as the only meanes, of ſafety to Themſelves, comfort to their afflicted <hi>King,</hi> and peace to theſe diſtreſſed <hi>Kingdoms;</hi> which I ſhall indeavour to prove by ſtrength of <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, though it bee a <hi>Maxim</hi> among godleſſe <hi>Stateſmen,</hi> never to truſt <hi>Princes</hi> whom they have highly offended: yet if the <hi>Independent Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees</hi> ſhould have no other aſſurance upon <hi>Agreement,</hi> than his <hi>Majeſtie's</hi> bare word for their <hi>Jndempuity,</hi> I am confident they might truſt him; it being a knowne <hi>Principle</hi> ingrafted in his nature, not only by <hi>morall</hi> Impreſſion, but alſo by <hi>Chriſtian</hi> perſwaſion, to <hi>forgive</hi> thoſe that have <hi>perſecuted him, and diſpightfully <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſed him:</hi> For, undoubtedly, the whole Courſe of his life hath manifeſted him (if men would lay aſide their <hi>Splene,</hi> and but ſpeake their <hi>Conſciences</hi>) to bee of a moſt <hi>gracious inclination,</hi> equall to any of his <hi>Predeceſſors,</hi> and an exact patern of true <hi>Clemency</hi> to ſucceeding <hi>Generations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, there is no doubt, but that upon Termes of <hi>Agreement, his Majesty</hi> will condeſcend to give any <hi>reall aſſurance</hi> for their ſecurity that ſhall in reaſon bee required; that is, ſo it extend not to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringement of his <hi>juſt Rights</hi> and royall <hi>Prerogative:</hi> For, it muſt bee ever ſuppoſed, that where an <hi>Accommodation</hi> is intended betwixt <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe</hi> Parties, there muſt bee a <hi>Condeſcenſion</hi> on both <hi>ſides,</hi> wherein the ordinary Principles of right <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Equity</hi> muſt bee the <hi>Rule:</hi> For, if either ſide keep to any one <hi>extreme,</hi> the old <hi>enmity</hi> will never want <hi>Fuell,</hi> and ſo the very <hi>Pretences</hi> of <hi>Accommodation</hi> will bee utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and end in more furious <hi>flames</hi> of <hi>Diſſenſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, there is a neceſſity of their <hi>Complyance</hi> with his <hi>Majesty,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the hatred of the People is ſo great, that if once they receive a <hi>Foile</hi> upon <hi>Battell;</hi> there is little poſſibility of recruiting, when the Hearts and purſes of both <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Country</hi> are ſhut againſt them: And therefore it were madnes for men to ſet their whole <hi>Stock</hi> at one <hi>Cast,</hi> and hazard the fortune of themſelves and Friends, upon the uncertain, chance of one ſingle <hi>Conflict;</hi> whereas <hi>wiſe</hi> men, before they pitch upon <hi>Enterprizes</hi> of ſo high a <hi>Nature,</hi> caſt about rather how to repaire them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon occaſion of <hi>loſſe,</hi> than dream altogether of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictory:</hi> For, ſuch a provident <hi>Jealouſy</hi> uſually leads men to fafety, whilſt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident <hi>imaginary</hi> proſperity of <hi>Fooles</hi> deſtroyes them.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, None can have greater cauſe of <hi>Jealouſie</hi> touching the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of their owne <hi>Affaires,</hi> than the preſent <hi>ruling Grandees</hi> now have: For, beſides the inſtability of their condition in reſpect of contrary Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors and <hi>parties</hi> ready to ingage againſt them at home, it is viſible, that they will bee invaded from abroad. The <hi>Covenant-Faction</hi> of the <hi>Scots</hi> are concerned in point of <hi>Intereſt,</hi> to wage war againſt them, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of their party againe in <hi>England;</hi> and his Majeſties Party in <hi>Scotland</hi> will not (as indeed they ought not) ſtand <hi>neutrall:</hi> And
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114752:8"/>though they have great hopes here, that the difference between his <hi>Majeſtie's</hi> Party and the <hi>Covenanters</hi> there, touching the Nature of an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement</hi> againſt <hi>England,</hi> may riſe ſo high, as by buſying them againſt each other, to keep them from ingaging this way at all; yet rather than ſuffer things to remaine at this paſſe in <hi>England,</hi> it is evident they will ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſede all <hi>bandyings</hi> among themſelves, and conſider of ſome <hi>middle</hi> way, wherein to mannage their <hi>Counſels</hi> and reſolutions, to bee revenged up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Independent</hi> Uſurpers. Beſides, it is very obſervable, that the late falling away in <hi>Ireland,</hi> may from a <hi>ceſſation,</hi> proceed to a perfect <hi>Peace</hi> with the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and then both joyne in one againſt the <hi>Houſes</hi> for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of his Majeſty. In the mean time, the <hi>Ceſſation</hi> will make way for <hi>Supplyes</hi> &amp; <hi>auxiliary</hi> Forces out of that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> to joyn with any <hi>diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented</hi> Party in this; where it is evident, that the People are ſo far exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, that they will joyne with the <hi>Scots, Iriſh;</hi> yea, or the <hi>Turk,</hi> upon hope of freeing themſelves &amp; reſtoring their <hi>King,</hi> rather than continue in thraldom, at the will and pleaſure of their preſent <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Maſters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, though the <hi>Houſes</hi> have voted the ſending of Forces over to hold <hi>play</hi> with <hi>Inchiquin</hi> in <hi>Munſter,</hi> and ſo to divert his intentions from <hi>England;</hi> yet People are not ſo ſilly, but to ſee, they are ſo far unable to raiſe, or keep up an <hi>Army</hi> in that <hi>Country,</hi> that they want wherewithall to mainteine their owne in this. And moreover, they are now in ſo ill a condition to ſpare men, that they dare not part with any conſiderable peece of this <hi>Army</hi> to reduce the <hi>Welſh,</hi> for feare that if themſelves were left naked, they might be ſurprized unawares; knowing this, that there is no ſitting, without a powerfull <hi>Army</hi> to guard them; whereof they are not a little conſcious, as appeares by drawing up the <hi>major part</hi> of the <hi>Army,</hi> into <hi>Quarters,</hi> at a neare diſtance about the <hi>City.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixthly, as they have innumerable cauſes of <hi>fear</hi> from others, they wil find little ground of <hi>ſecurity</hi> even among themſelves: For, if we conſider the conſtitution of the Army, in the ſeveral parts of it, it appears to be an <hi>ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregate</hi> of differing <hi>intereſts, opinions,</hi> &amp; <hi>perſwaſions;</hi> among whom the <hi>Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees</hi> have the leſſe numerous <hi>party,</hi> being over-ballanced by the <hi>Levellers,</hi> and others of the inferior <hi>Officers</hi> &amp; private Souldiers, whom we may rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon as men of <hi>fortune,</hi> who continue in the <hi>Army,</hi> not out of any devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or affection to the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> but only for ſubſiſtence, &amp; therefore being rather affectionated to his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> will be ready (as they receive opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity) to ſhew themſelves in his <hi>ſervice.</hi> And as for the <hi>Levellers,</hi> though all the induſtry in the world be uſed, to pacifie them from the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of former injuries, and draw them in to a conjunction with the <hi>Grandees,</hi> againſt the <hi>King,</hi> and the <hi>Scots;</hi> yet it is probable they will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſell their <hi>bloud</hi> and <hi>fellow-ſubjects</hi> at ſo vile a rate, as to purchaſe a ſure dominion for ſuch <hi>tyrannicall Masters;</hi> who, when they have help't them to do the <hi>work,</hi> will be ready (as they did before) to cruſh them, and pay them their wages, with perpetuall <hi>ſlavery.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:114752:9"/>
               <p>Seventhly, their Party is very inconſiderable at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the <hi>Houſe</hi> being no longer theirs, than whileſt they over-awe it by <hi>force,</hi> as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves well know: ſo that if it happen, the <hi>Scots</hi> come in, the <hi>Preſbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> party being once back't with an <hi>Army,</hi> will ſoon <hi>out-vote</hi> them. And then the time will come on, wherein they ſhall be called to an accompt for all their forcible <hi>attempts</hi> upon the <hi>Houſes</hi> and the <hi>city;</hi> and thoſe <hi>Members</hi> that went and joyned with them therein, bee brought upon the ſtage for <hi>breach of truſt,</hi> and have the ſhame of <hi>high-Treaſon</hi> retort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon themſelves, and their <hi>Auguſt</hi>-Ingagement.</p>
               <p>Eighthly, by a timely <hi>agreement,</hi> they may ſettle an <hi>Intereſt</hi> with his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> to make themſelves certainly great; foraſmuch as it is poſſible both their <hi>Intereſts</hi> may ſtand together (with diſcretion) entire, by the reſtitution of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and upon aſſurance given for <hi>liberty of conſcience,</hi> within ſober limits.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, his <hi>Majeſty</hi> is the very <hi>baſis</hi> of peace, and the balancing power to all <hi>Parties</hi> in this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and without him no ſettlement can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected; and with whatſoever ſide he joynes, that will aſſuredly prevaile. To manifeſt the truth thereof, let it be remembred of what concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment his <hi>complyance</hi> was to the <hi>Independents,</hi> in ſubduing their oppoſite <hi>Faction</hi> both in the <hi>Houſes</hi> and the <hi>city,</hi> while he reſided among them in the <hi>Army.</hi> And as by this meanes, at that time, they advanced themſelves to the height of <hi>fortune;</hi> ſo now that they are, in the eyes of all the world, in a <hi>declining</hi> condition, they may (if they pleaſe) give a <hi>check</hi> to the <hi>triumph</hi> of their <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> adverſaries, by applying themſelves more cordially and ſincerely to the ſame way of <hi>complyance</hi> with his <hi>Majeſty.</hi> This wil be a means to oblige him, and his <hi>Party</hi> ſo far that all injuries be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing buried in <hi>oblivion,</hi> the people gladded by the return of a long deſired <hi>peace,</hi> the old enmity and malice will be ſoon abated, and the <hi>Royall Party</hi> and themſelves ſtrengthened in one, by an addition of the whole Body of the <hi>Nobility, Gentry</hi> and <hi>Commonalty,</hi> againſt all <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, either within, or without the <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From all which we may ſum up this <hi>concluſion;</hi> that as his <hi>Majeſty</hi> is obliged in point of <hi>intereſt</hi> to wave all <hi>Preſbyteriall</hi> Ingagements, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour an agreement with the <hi>Independent:</hi> ſo likewiſe it appears, that the true <hi>intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Independent</hi> Party is, with all ſpeed to recall thoſe prodigious <hi>Votes</hi> of <hi>Non-Addreſſe,</hi> and apply themſelves unto his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,</hi> with ſuch moderate deſires, that may ſtand as well with his <hi>honor,</hi> as their <hi>ſafety,</hi> &amp; be a means to remove all <hi>jealouſie</hi> &amp; <hi>diſtaſt</hi> betwixt him and them; and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on juſt and neceſſary <hi>grounds</hi> lay a ſure <hi>foundation</hi> for a <hi>laſting peace.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>III. <hi>Reaſons drawn from the</hi> Intereſt <hi>of the</hi> Presbyterian Party <hi>in</hi> England.</head>
               <p>WHence it was, and for what ends, the <hi>deſigne</hi> of <hi>Preſbytery</hi> was firſt brought into this <hi>Nation,</hi> Time the mother of <hi>Truth</hi> hath at length fully manifeſted: for, as the <hi>pretences</hi> of it were high &amp; glorious, ſo the iſſue hath been fallacious &amp; <hi>diſhonorable,</hi> and to it we muſt aſcribe the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:114752:9"/>originall cauſe and continuance of all our miſeries.</p>
               <p>That it arrived to ſuch a hight in the opinions of many, as to be cryed up for the onely pattern of <hi>Government</hi> under the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> muſt be imputed to the <hi>blind zeal</hi> of ſome, and the <hi>deceitfulneſſe</hi> of others, rather then the intention of its <hi>founder,</hi> Maſter <hi>Calvin:</hi> For it doth not appear that he ever ſtretcht his <hi>model</hi> ſo far, as the neceſſity and univerſality of a <hi>divine right;</hi> but ſeems onely to have hewen part of the building out of the rock of the Scriptures, according to the <hi>literall</hi> ſignification, and pieced up the reſidue by politick and prudentiall rules, ſuch as he conceived might ſound neereſt the Text, and ſerve moſt conveniently to cement the disjoynted members of that broken and tumultuous Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>Geneva,</hi> into an entire and well compacted <hi>body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was no ſooner lick't into <hi>form</hi> there, but (as it is the fate of all things <hi>new</hi>) it began to be much extol'd and admired, and the fame thereof ſpreading it ſelf in <hi>England</hi> (as well as in other parts) wrought in many of our Country-men an <hi>itching</hi> deſire to go thither, and obſerve the manners and cuſtomes of the <hi>Government;</hi> where, of <hi>Spectators</hi> they ſoon became <hi>Proſelites,</hi> and returning home with new affections and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, had an <hi>evil eye</hi> upon the ancient Apoſtolicall government of <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy,</hi> which they proſecuted with invective <hi>Libels</hi> from the <hi>Preſſe</hi> and <hi>Pulpit,</hi> as <hi>Antichristian;</hi> in the mean time extolling their new <hi>Diana,</hi> in hope to bring better advantage thereby unto themſelves, then they could hope to <hi>attain</hi> under the <hi>government</hi> of Biſhops: and in proceſſe of time, their <hi>Doctrines</hi> being brought into reputation by the addition of an <hi>artificiall</hi> and <hi>counterfeit piety,</hi> they ſtole away the hearts of many <hi>well-meaning</hi> people throughout the Kingdom, whom they poyſoned with diſaffection to the preſent <hi>Government.</hi> So here was the riſe of the old <hi>Presbyters,</hi> which paſſed heretofore under the names of <hi>Non conformiſts,</hi> or <hi>Puritans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Manifold were the <hi>Bickerings</hi> which they had with the Biſhops during the reigns of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and King <hi>James;</hi> yet the <hi>Faction</hi> was then kept under <hi>hatches</hi> by great care and policy, as it was likewiſe all the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part of the reign of our gracious Sovereign <hi>CHARLES,</hi> though the <hi>humours</hi> began to work more ſtrongly then ever; inſomuch, that having gained a <hi>party</hi> in every <hi>Parliament;</hi> which preſumed to inſiſt upon very high particulars of <hi>Government</hi> both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> and queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch <hi>Officers</hi> of both as ſtood in the way of their <hi>deſigne,</hi> his <hi>Majesty</hi> was neceſſitated, by reaſon of thoſe audacious and factious proceedings, to a frequent <hi>diſſolution</hi> of Parliaments; which though they publikely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed againſt, yet inwardly they were glad enough of it, working
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114752:10"/>advantage thereby, to ſcandalize his <hi>Majesty,</hi> in the opinion of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as one <hi>utterly diſaffected to Parliaments,</hi> and that intended to govern altogether by an <hi>arbitrary power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This and other <hi>Scandals</hi> were treaſured up againſt the time, wherein they hoped to have occaſion to uſe them; but having often tryed their own ſingle ſtrength to be too weak to ſhake the <hi>Government,</hi> then the <hi>Grandees</hi> of the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> not knowing otherwiſe to repair their <hi>broken for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes,</hi> began to have recourſe unto the <hi>Scots,</hi> a people as needy as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and who (it was preſumed) would be glad to entertain any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to mend their <hi>Fortunes,</hi> and eſtabliſh an <hi>Intereſt</hi> in this <hi>Nation:</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, their hope was the greater to thrive among the <hi>Scots,</hi> becauſe they were a people that had been diſcountenanced and diſcontented by the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and had embraced the ſame form of <hi>Government</hi> that was aimed at by themſelves, and therefore could not but be willing to contribute their beſt aſſiſtance toward the ſettlement of it in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore the <hi>motion</hi> was no ſooner made from hence, but it found joyfull entertainment in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and Counſels were mutually imparted by the grand <hi>Presbyters</hi> on both ſides; and in fine it was agreed, that <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> ſhould be the <hi>ſtalking-horſe</hi> to the whole <hi>Deſign.</hi> The <hi>aime</hi> of the <hi>Scots</hi> therein, was the gaining of Treaſure, and an union of intereſt with <hi>England:</hi> The <hi>aime</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Presbyters, was the quelling of their <hi>Oppſites</hi> at Court, and ſupplanting them in their <hi>Offices,</hi> the deſtruction of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and with it, of <hi>Monarchy;</hi> and the enriching of themſelves with the Wealth of the Kingdom, the Revenues of the <hi>Crown,</hi> and the Goods of the <hi>Church;</hi> all which become a prey unto that monſter of <hi>Presbytery,</hi> till it was wreſted out of their jawes, by the new brethren of the <hi>Independent</hi> party.</p>
               <p>By which brief <hi>draught</hi> of Diſcourſe it appears, that as a great part of the Commons of <hi>England</hi> have been drawn in upon <hi>religious pretences</hi> to the faction of <hi>Presbytery,</hi> to ſerve <hi>worldly ends;</hi> ſo now that the hypocriſie and diſſimulation of thoſe proceedings is manifeſt unto the world, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt the true <hi>intereſt</hi> of all honeſt-meaning <hi>Presbyters</hi> in <hi>England</hi> is the very ſame with that of the Nation in generall, to <hi>ſeek peace and enſue it,</hi> to quit all conſiderations of <hi>ſiding</hi> or <hi>faction,</hi> to open their eyes and ſee how they have been deceived, to loath the vanity, and prevent the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of all engagements in and for <hi>Presbytery;</hi> to endeavour ſimply the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and to joyn with any for that end, but with none that are contrary; and alſo to content themſelves with a <hi>regulated Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy,</hi> for theſe following Reaſons.</p>
               <p>Firſt, ſeeing it is moſt true, that there can be no ſettlement in this
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114752:10"/>Kingdom, but by a compliance with the <hi>royall</hi> intereſt, it is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impoſſible to expect <hi>peace,</hi> if a deſign be ſtill cheriſhed for the eſtabliſhing <hi>Presbytery</hi> becauſe of that abſolute <hi>antipathy</hi> (or incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility) betwixt <hi>Monarchicall</hi> and <hi>Presbyteriall</hi> Government, as I have manifeſted before: <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Belial, light</hi> and <hi>darkneſſe</hi> may as ſoon agree together; and therefore it muſt not be expected, that his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> ſhould yeeld up his <hi>Honour, Conſcience</hi> and <hi>Crown,</hi> in ſacrifice to ſo pernicious a <hi>rivall</hi> in his <hi>Prerogative.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, if there be a freſh engaging for <hi>Presbytery</hi> to cruſh <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency,</hi> what more hope of <hi>peace</hi> have we when this <hi>prevailing party</hi> ſhall be down, and the other up again? are we not where we were before? ſhall not his <hi>Majeſty</hi> remain as lyable as ever to the old vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atious <hi>Popoſitions?</hi> and have not the Presbyters of the <hi>Kirk</hi> told us plainly beforehand, that they are reſolved, he ſhall ſign all their <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires</hi> before his reſolution to the exerciſe of his <hi>Regall power?</hi> what then may we expect from <hi>Presbytery,</hi> after all the miſeries and deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of a ſecond War, but that his <hi>Majeſty</hi> ſhall remain in <hi>durance,</hi> as he did at <hi>Holdenby,</hi> or does now in the <hi>Iſland,</hi> without all hope of remedy to himſelf, or end of thoſe intolerable <hi>oppreſſions</hi> lying upon this afflicted Kingdom?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, it being cleer, that the deſign of a <hi>Presbytery</hi> hath been carried on meerly for the private ends of particular men, what mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is it for men that pretend <hi>wiſdom, Religion</hi> and <hi>godlineſſe,</hi> to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard themſelves and their Eſtates, to draw on the guilt of innocent blood by embroyling their fellow ſubjects, and infringe their <hi>Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations</hi> to their <hi>Soveraign,</hi> by proſtituting their <hi>conſciences, purſes</hi> and <hi>endeavours,</hi> to ſerve the ambition of a few, whoſe practiſes (when they are inveſted with power) will be (as they ever have been) to make them ſhare with others in the <hi>common calamity</hi> at preſent, and intaile <hi>ſlavery</hi> upon their <hi>Poſterity</hi> for ever?</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>Presbytery</hi> whereſoever it ſettles, is deſtructive of <hi>liberty,</hi> by reaſon of that <hi>popiſh trick</hi> taken up by the <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> in drawing all ſecular affaires within the compaſſe of their ſpirituall juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and this they do by means of that awe wherein they hold the conſciences of the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> and <hi>People;</hi> the one being lyable as well as the other, by <hi>excommunications</hi> and <hi>ſuſpenſions,</hi> to be exploded as <hi>ſcandalous ſinners,</hi> when they pleaſe to pronounce them ſuch; as appears by that large extent of their Authority in judging of <hi>ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſins,</hi> which reaches almoſt to every action of humane life: ſo that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114752:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:114752:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:114752:12"/>all the reſt of the Kingdom, beſides their <hi>favourites</hi> (from the <hi>King</hi> to the <hi>Beggar</hi>) muſt ſtoop like aſſes, to be ridden by a few ambitious <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Lay-ignoramuſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly, a <hi>regulated Epiſcopacy</hi> muſt be the onely government for this Nation, in regard it is moſt ſuitable to the conſtitution of the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> and the <hi>Lawes</hi> of the Land (whereto through continuance of time it hath a very neer relation) and alſo to the humours and good liking of the people, inſomuch that the <hi>Brethren</hi> of the contrary way after all their art, induſtry and perſwaſion, have found by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that it is impoſſible to force any other upon them; therefore without all controverſie, a <hi>Biſhop</hi> mortified and pruned of his <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities,</hi> moderated in the juriſdiction of his Court, and the <hi>compulſive</hi> power, and aſſiſted by the <hi>Clergy</hi> of his <hi>Dioceſſe,</hi> will in the end ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be the moſt excellent <hi>Governour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixtly, if any <hi>Presbyter</hi> object, that he hath ſworn to the extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Biſhops, he may do well to conſider the unlawfulneſſe of ſuch an Oath, it having never been enjoyned by any lawfull <hi>authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> but expreſly without it, and againſt it; and moreover, to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of that which is lawfull, <hi>viz.</hi> the government of the <hi>Church,</hi> confirmed by the <hi>Lawes</hi> of the Land; which appears alſo by the undoubted teſtimony of ancient <hi>Records</hi> and later <hi>Hiſtories,</hi> to have been continued with an <hi>univerſell, uninterrupted, unqueſtioned</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion in all the <hi>Churches of God,</hi> and in all Kingdoms that have been called <hi>Christian</hi> throughout the whole world, for fifteen hundred yeers together, without any conſiderable oppoſition made againſt it; and which, if it be not of <hi>divine right,</hi> hath a fairer pretenſion, and may lay a juſter title and claim to a <hi>divine inſtitution,</hi> then any other <hi>form of Government</hi> can do: and therefore it having been wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily of ſuch eſteem in all Times and Places, and eſtabliſhed by <hi>Law,</hi> certainly an <hi>Oath</hi> binding to extirpate it without <hi>Law</hi> and againſt <hi>Law,</hi> is utterly unlawfull, and ſo rather to be repented of, then ſtubbornly maintained.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, by ſtanding out for a <hi>Presbytery,</hi> they give the more hopes and encouragement to the <hi>Independent</hi> party, to perſiſt in a way of obſtinacy againſt his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and oppreſſion of the <hi>Subject;</hi> becauſe it will be a means to hinder a cordiall joynt engaging betwixt the <hi>Presbyters</hi> and the <hi>Royall party,</hi> and enflame the old <hi>enmity,</hi> to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of each other, whileſt <hi>Independents</hi> gather ſtrength and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to triumph in the ruines of their <hi>diviſion;</hi> whereas by a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114752:12"/>ſpeedy <hi>compliance</hi> with his <hi>Majeſties intereſt,</hi> they may quell the pride of <hi>Independency,</hi> and either fetch them down to a compoſition with his <hi>Majeſty;</hi> or in caſe they continue <hi>perverſe,</hi> be ſurely enabled to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell them out of the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, by a ſincere, abſolute <hi>cloſe</hi> with his Majeſty upon rationall grounds, they do no more then what the <hi>prevailing party</hi> among their <hi>Brethren</hi> the <hi>Scots,</hi> pretend to engage for (and truly, if their <hi>intents</hi> be otherwiſe, they will finde but cold entertainment in <hi>England;</hi>) therefore if the Presbyters of <hi>England</hi> would but acquit themſelves like reaſonable men, the work of reſtoring his <hi>Majeſty</hi> might be done without the <hi>Scots,</hi> and all thoſe miſeries and inconveniences be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyded, which muſt certainly follow the admiſſion of a <hi>forreign Army;</hi> which, beſides the <hi>preſſures</hi> that they muſt bring upon the exhauſted <hi>Northen parts,</hi> will expect a large retribution of <hi>Treaſure</hi> for a reward of their <hi>engaging,</hi> and (perhaps) not depart in quiet, but upon ſuch <hi>Termes,</hi> as may be exceedingly prejudiciall and diſhonourable to the Engliſh Nation.</p>
               <p>From hence I once again infer, the true <hi>intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Presbyters,</hi> is to counter-work the <hi>Independents</hi> in their <hi>intereſt,</hi> which they now drive againſt his <hi>Majeſty;</hi> and to this end, to quicken themſelves to a joynt engaging with the <hi>royall party,</hi> as the onely means to beat down the <hi>ambition</hi> of the ruling Grandees of the <hi>Independent</hi> party, to prevent the miſeries of a long-languiſhing War, with the in conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences of a <hi>Scottiſh</hi> incurſion; and alſo to procure the ſpeedy ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>King</hi> in his juſt <hi>Rights,</hi> and the Kingdoms in firm <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>tranquility.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>IIII.</hi> Reaſons drawn from the <hi>intereſt</hi> of the City of <hi>London.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>This great and populous <hi>City</hi> is the <hi>epitome</hi> of the Kingdom, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of as it is a <hi>member,</hi> it hath the ſame common <hi>intereſt</hi> with the whole; yet being more excellent then any other <hi>part,</hi> by reaſon of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance of the reſt upon it, as being the principall Fountain of <hi>Traffick;</hi> and alſo by reaſon of its abundance of <hi>Wealth,</hi> the grand Priviledges of their Charter, and the multitude of their <hi>Revenues</hi> and <hi>Inhabitants,</hi> they have much the greater ſhare in the common <hi>intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Nation;</hi> which is, <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Proſperity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſpeciall <hi>intereſt</hi> of this <hi>City</hi> is a <hi>free trade,</hi> as well within, as without the Kingdom: The onely enemy thereto is a <hi>civill warre,</hi> which deſtroyes <hi>commerce</hi> betwixt man and man; whereof the <hi>Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:114752:13"/>have had ſad experience theſe <hi>tumultuous times</hi> by the decay of <hi>Trading,</hi> the like hath not been many hundred yeers. So that the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way to recover againe, is to endeavour after a happy <hi>Peace;</hi> and ſeeing there is no poſſibility of attaining it, but by an eſtabliſhment of his <hi>Majeſtie,</hi> I ſhall preſent them with a few <hi>Conſiderations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, they may doe well to remember, how they were cheated heretofore with religious <hi>pretences</hi> into an <hi>Ingagement</hi> againſt his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and how that the whole Kingdome muſt owe its ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation to their warlike preparations and <hi>Contributions.</hi> Therfore as it hath been their unhappineſſe to have the firſt hand in driving away the <hi>King,</hi> and un-ſetling the Kingdom; ſo let them account it their <hi>honor,</hi> to be active and induſtrious in bringing him back again, and to ſettle him in peace on the throne of the <hi>Kingdome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, in effecting this, they ought to have reſpect onely to the <hi>Royall Intereſt,</hi> without the mixture of any <hi>factious</hi> ingaging what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, under pretence of <hi>Covenant, &amp;c.</hi> leſt while they ſeem to act in the behalfe of his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> they unawares drive on the deſign again of ſome particular <hi>Faction,</hi> inſtead of the <hi>Publick</hi> Good, and ſo leave open a <hi>Gap</hi> ſtill to <hi>Diviſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, in caſe that the <hi>Scots</hi> come into this <hi>Kingdome</hi> againe, the Citizens ought to ſee very narrowly to the <hi>Principles</hi> of their ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ere they condeſcend to ſupply, or countenance them, <hi>ſecretly</hi> or <hi>openly.</hi> If they come in with the old <hi>cheat</hi> of <hi>Reformation, Covenant</hi> and <hi>Presbytery,</hi> it will be the wiſdome of the <hi>Citie</hi> to conſider, that this will be but a new <hi>On-ſet</hi> to the firſt deſigne of <hi>Scotiſh</hi> incroaching up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt, and the maintaining of a <hi>Faction</hi> to ſerve the ends of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the ambition of a few <hi>Scotified Engliſh,</hi> whoſe Aymes have been and are, to ſhare Dominion with the <hi>Scots,</hi> to the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and prejudice of the <hi>Nation,</hi> and the ruine of <hi>Monarchy,</hi> the alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of <hi>Church-government</hi> (how ſpeciouſly ſoever ſet forth) being but a buſineſſe ſubordinate to the <hi>private ends</hi> of particular <hi>Grandees</hi> among the <hi>Laity</hi> and obſcure <hi>Rabbies</hi> of the <hi>Clergy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, they may be pleaſed to obſerve, that the <hi>Game</hi> plaid hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto betwixt the two <hi>Factions</hi> of <hi>Presbytery</hi> and <hi>Independency,</hi> hath been onely which of them ſhould be our <hi>Riders;</hi> and its to be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed now that all the ſtrugling of the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> againſt the preſent ruling <hi>Grandees,</hi> is not by diſmounting of them to free us, but onely to get themſelves againe into the <hi>Saddle,</hi> that they may domineer o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and then what comfort will the <hi>City</hi> or others
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:114752:13"/>reap by all their paines and expences? Therefore it concerns the <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens</hi> to looke well before they leape, and not to be deluded any longer with the ſtale <hi>pretences</hi> of a glorious <hi>Reformation;</hi> the end whereof is nothing elſe but oppreſſion and confuſion both of <hi>King</hi> and <hi>People.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly, the <hi>Citizens</hi> may doe well to conſider, what little benefit they are like to gaine unto themſelves, in <hi>lieu</hi> of all that <hi>miſchiefe</hi> that they will bring upon <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kingdome,</hi> if the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Faction ſhall prevaile againe. It may be it will ſomewhat tickle them for a time, to be revenged on the <hi>Independent</hi> party; and 'tis like they ſhall have their <hi>Members</hi> out of the <hi>Tower,</hi> and be put into the repoſſeſſion of that and their <hi>Militia,</hi> ſo long as they imploy all to the behoofe and benefit of the <hi>Faction.</hi> But if the <hi>Presbyter-Citizens</hi> ſhall after a little time, upon the diſcovery of the Inconveniences brought upon the whole Kingdom, by the ſtanding out againſt his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> in point of <hi>Presbytery,</hi> begin once to grow diſcontented and weary of their new <hi>Maſters,</hi> they may ſurely expect to be ſerved the ſame meaſure that is now meted unto them by the Rulers of <hi>Independency;</hi> it being a Rule with all <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers,</hi> no longer to countenance any that they have drawne into their <hi>Party,</hi> then they are willing to run on with them in <hi>Deſigne;</hi> but if once they begin to flag, to bury all their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer merits in oblivion; alſo to reckon them as <hi>enemies,</hi> and uſe them accordingly.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, if they ſhall diſcover themſelves ſo farre, as to ingage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine for <hi>Presbytery,</hi> let the <hi>Deſigne</hi> be attended with never ſo many pretences of <hi>loyalty</hi> towards the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Poſterity,</hi> yet it being cleer notwithſtanding, that ſuch an <hi>Ingagement</hi> would be deſtructive to the <hi>Royall Intereſt,</hi> his <hi>Majeſty</hi> and the <hi>Royall party</hi> can looke upon them no otherwiſe, then as abſolutely <hi>diſloyall,</hi> and reſolved to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue their Rebellious courſes. And then if it ſhall ſo happen (as probably it may) that there be a <hi>Complyance</hi> betwixt the <hi>Royall</hi> and <hi>Independent</hi> Party, the <hi>Doore</hi> will be in a manner <hi>bolted</hi> againſt any <hi>accommodation</hi> betwixt them and his <hi>Majeſtie;</hi> and then by the union of thoſe two <hi>Powers</hi> before named, the <hi>Pillars</hi> of their <hi>Faction</hi> (both <hi>Scottiſh</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi>) being ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ken, and driven out of the <hi>KING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DOME,</hi> They will remaine wholly at his MAJESTIES mercy, touching the forfeiture of their <hi>Charter</hi> and <hi>Priviledges,</hi> &amp;c. and give him opportunity to bethinke himſelfe of ſuch wayes and meanes to quell their Pride, and ſuch meanes as
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114752:14"/>may ſecure himſelf and his Succeſſors from the rage of all turbulent and ſeditious humours in time to come.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, the <hi>Citizens</hi> ought to beſtir themſelves with ſuch ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity, and give ſuch teſtimonies of their <hi>loyalty,</hi> as may ſerve to abate the <hi>career</hi> of our <hi>Independent</hi> Grandees, who will otherwiſe never be brought down to a <hi>compliance</hi> with his <hi>Majeſty:</hi> and to this end, it will be their wiſdom to pretend high toward an engaging any way, rather then endure them at this paſſe any longer; but ſtill not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding to reſerve within themſelves a cordiall tender reſpect to the true <hi>intereſt</hi> of his <hi>Majeſty:</hi> Moreover, if the <hi>caſe</hi> ſhall ſo ſtand, that an <hi>agreement</hi> be concluded betwixt his <hi>Majeſty</hi> and the <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents</hi> (which certainly will be happieſt for this <hi>Nation,</hi> if it can poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be effected) then the <hi>Citizens</hi> ought not to let their ſpleens boil with the remembrance injuries received from this <hi>Faction;</hi> nor flatter themſelves with imaginary benefits, which they ſuppoſe they might enjoy by advancing the other but lay aſide all emulation and reſpect of <hi>faction</hi> on the one ſide or the other, and be ready to applaud any courſe, which his <hi>Majeſty</hi> ſhall judge moſt convenient for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of theſe <hi>unhappy differences.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, ſince the reſtoring and ſelling of his <hi>Majeſty</hi> is the onely way of true <hi>peace,</hi> then in caſe the <hi>Independents</hi> ſhould continue obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate (to the laſt) againſt any <hi>agreement,</hi> it concerns all the honeſt and wiſe men of <hi>London,</hi> to be wary upon what terms they admit of a <hi>Scottiſh engagement,</hi> and not to be drawn in as they were formerly; but rather to obſerve the motions and directions of the <hi>royall party,</hi> and conform themſelves wholly that way, as being the ſafeſt, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſteſt and moſt honourable, becauſe free from faction and by-ends, and which hath for its ſole end, the reſtitution of his <hi>Majeſty</hi> and his royall <hi>Posterity,</hi> the preſervation of the <hi>Church,</hi> and the eſtabliſhment of true Religion, Peace and Liberty throughout his <hi>Majeſtes</hi> Realms and Dominions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>V.</hi> Reaſons drawn from the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The People of <hi>England</hi> being fully ſatisfied, that the deſign for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of <hi>Church-government,</hi> under pretence of <hi>Reformation,</hi> was firſt ſet on foot by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Grandees, meerly for am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious, worldly ends and reſpects; and the <hi>Scots</hi> having had ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent experience of the ſtoutneſſe of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſtomacks, that they will by no means digeſt the <hi>Presbyteriall government,</hi> and ſince it is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:114752:14"/>look't on by all knowing men, as abſolutely inconſiſtent with, and deſtructive of <hi>Monarchy,</hi> without doubt it concernes the <hi>Scots</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinke themſelves of ſome other way wherby to ſettle an <hi>Intereſt</hi> and Inter-courſe with this <hi>Nation,</hi> than by introducing a <hi>Presbytery,</hi> where it is ſo extreamly diſtaſted, by the <hi>generality</hi> of the People.</p>
               <p>That there is no way for the <hi>Scots</hi> to ſettle a beneficiall and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Intereſt</hi> here, but by an abſolute and ſincere <hi>Cloſe</hi> with the Royall <hi>Intereſt,</hi> I ſhall manifeſt by ſeverall Reaſons:</p>
               <p>Firſt, if they come in, and declare (in a mixed manner) for the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Covenant,</hi> they give the world to underſtand, that they come but to Act the old <hi>Cheat</hi> over again, ſeeing the <hi>Covenant</hi> (though there be words in it mentioning the <hi>Honour and happineſſe of the King and his Poſterity</hi>) would prove (in effect) the deſtruction of both: For if it works not an abſolute change of Government in the <hi>State,</hi> as well as the <hi>Church;</hi> yet it is cleer, that it will regulate it into a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture farre beneath the dignity and condition of a <hi>Monarchy.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore upon ſuch Termes, they will loſe that aſſiſtance, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they might have from the Royall Party in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, by ſo <hi>declaring,</hi> they will draw the <hi>Curtaine</hi> now placed betwixt them and us, and give a perfect diſcovery of their <hi>Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> and we ſhall conclude, that their <hi>ayme</hi> is no wiſe at the good of his <hi>Majeſtie,</hi> but onely to ſerve their owne corrupt <hi>Intereſts.</hi> And we ſhall beleeve they bring in an <hi>Army</hi> for no other end, but to back their Party of <hi>Presbytery</hi> in the <hi>Houſe</hi> and the <hi>City,</hi> ſo to cruſh the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite Faction of <hi>Independencie,</hi> and then by removing the <hi>King</hi> to one of his <hi>Houſes,</hi> reduce him and the Affaires of the Kingdome in <hi>Statu quo prius,</hi> as when he was at <hi>Holdenby;</hi> where he ſhall languiſh in the condition of a <hi>Priſoner,</hi> as long as he lives, or (at leaſt) as long as they reigne; it being reſolved on before hand, that he ſhall not be reſtored to the exerciſe of <hi>regall Power,</hi> till he have ſigned their <hi>Deſires,</hi> and <hi>Propoſitions;</hi> which his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> hath ſo often declared to be againſt his <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Conſcience.</hi> And then what may the <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters</hi> expect, but that the inraged People, having been ſo often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded, and tyred in expectation of a <hi>Settlement,</hi> will take the firſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to riſe all as one Man, to baniſh them and their <hi>Faction</hi> out of <hi>England,</hi> and upon their ruines reſtore both <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> to their former <hi>Liberty?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, it ſeemes not to be the Reſolution of the <hi>Covenant-A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bettors</hi> onely in <hi>Scotland,</hi> but it is declared by that <hi>Party</hi> which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends higheſt for his <hi>Majestie</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and delivered in by them,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:114752:15"/>in their Anſwer to the <hi>Deſires</hi> of the <hi>Kirke;</hi> That they reſolve <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to put into his <hi>Majeſties</hi> hands, or any other, ſuch power, whereby the <hi>Ends</hi> of the <hi>Covenant</hi> may be obſtructed; but that his <hi>Majeſty</hi> ſhall before any <hi>Ingagement,</hi> give aſſurance under <hi>Hand</hi> and <hi>Seale,</hi> for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and Succeſſors, to agree to certain <hi>Acts,</hi> injoyning the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, Presbbyterian</hi> Government, &amp;c. and never to endeavour the change thereof. Which <hi>reſolution</hi> of theirs gives us cauſe to ſuſpect; that all the <hi>Bickerings</hi> heretofore between them and the <hi>Kirke,</hi> were but meer <hi>ventilations,</hi> acted on purpoſe to make the world beleeve ſome high <hi>Deſigne</hi> on foot there in the behalfe of his <hi>Majestie,</hi> and to feed the <hi>Royall</hi> Party with hopes of great matters from <hi>Scotland,</hi> that being held in ſuſpence, they might remaine the leſſe active, and give the <hi>Scots</hi> a more plauſible and eaſie Ingreſſe into <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, ſuch a <hi>Reſolution</hi> (if it once come to a publique <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi>) will make men apt to beleeve, that under his <hi>Majeſties</hi> name, thoſe royall <hi>Pretenders</hi> doe Act ſome <hi>particular Intereſts</hi> likewiſe, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then that of his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> and the <hi>Publique.</hi> And further, ſeeing <hi>Hamilton</hi> is the <hi>Chiefe</hi> among them, it cannot be judged very impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that He (who is a convicted Perſon, for aſpiring to the <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and who was ſo bold in the dayes of his <hi>Majeſties</hi> proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity, as to attempt it, and to that end (the better to compaſſe his <hi>Deſigne</hi>) had a hand in widening the diſtance betwixt his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> and the two <hi>Houſes,</hi> and alſo in imbroyling the two <hi>Kingdomes</hi>) ſhould take opportunity now in his <hi>Majeſties</hi> loweſt condition, and the preſent <hi>Diviſion,</hi> to weave in his owne ambitious <hi>Intereſt,</hi> in hope to bring his Affaires unto perfection. I cannot accuſe him; but if the <hi>Prieſtly Faction</hi> and his, doe cloſe with each other upon <hi>Covenant conſiderations,</hi> it is a ſhrewd <hi>ſuſpition:</hi> The agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them (in plaine Termes) is this; That if HAMILTON ſerve the <hi>Presbyterian Deſigne</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> the Presbyters of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes ſhall (in requitall) connive at his doings, or aſſiſt him in his deſigne upon the Crowne of <hi>Scotland;</hi> and ſo his <hi>Majestie</hi> ſhall become a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> to the <hi>Covetouſneſſe</hi> and <hi>Pride</hi> of his malicious <hi>Adverſaries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, by an immediate and abſolute Ingagement for his <hi>Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie,</hi> ſuch <hi>jealouſies</hi> as theſe will be quite taken away, and the hearts of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſo inclined and obliged to the <hi>Scots,</hi> that they will hezard both <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Eſtates</hi> in their aſſiſtance, and be willing by way of <hi>re-tribution,</hi> not onely to diſ-burſe toward the ſatisfaction
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:114752:15"/>of their <hi>Arreares,</hi> but yeeld alſo, that his <hi>Majestie</hi> ſhall gratifie them with ſuch other Rewards and ſpeciall <hi>Indulgences</hi> of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Favour</hi> in this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> as may tend highly to the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage</hi> of their <hi>Nation,</hi> even farre beyond what they may gaine by advancing their <hi>Presbyterian Intereſt;</hi> ſeeing it will be a long time ere the <hi>Kingdome</hi> can that way be ſtated, by reaſon of the contrary <hi>working humours,</hi> which will be ready to breake out ever and anon into <hi>new Inſurrections;</hi> whereby the <hi>faction</hi> will be ſo continually bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied at an exceſſive charge, and the People ſo impoveriſhed, that they will not be more unwilling then unable to raiſe ſuch vaſt ſums, as are neceſſary for their ſatisfaction; at moſt, not the <hi>tithe</hi> of that <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion</hi> which they may receive ſuddenly from the hands of the <hi>King,</hi> and with the love of the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, let not the <hi>Scots</hi> flatter themſelves with a conceit of ſeeling their <hi>Presbytery</hi> amongſt us, whether we will or no; for though they may do much by the ſtrength of their <hi>faction,</hi> yet both <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> of that gang may conſider, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> are a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant and <hi>generous people,</hi> impatient of the yoke; and though they may be beaten down for a time, yet if the Kingdom were divided into twenty parts, ſeeing (I am confident) at leaſt nineteen of them are againſt <hi>Presbytery,</hi> it cannot be in reaſon imagined, that a few <hi>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Punies,</hi> relying meerly upon <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Arms, ſhould be able to trample down the <hi>ſpirits</hi> of this our magnanimous Nation for ever; but rather, that when they have ſmarted again under <hi>Presbyterian-tyranny</hi> for a time, they may recollect themſelves with ſo much cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and ſucceſſe, as will enable them to drive away the <hi>Scots</hi> and their faction, and confine the laſt <hi>ſeene</hi> of war within the limits of <hi>Scotland,</hi> where it had its <hi>Originall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seventhly, though they may relie much upon a <hi>Party</hi> in the <hi>City,</hi> yet the <hi>Citizens</hi> eyes being well opened, to ſee that they have been made but <hi>ſtalking-horſes</hi> to other mens private ends, and been gul'd out of ſo many <hi>millions,</hi> onely to purchaſe <hi>ſlavery</hi> unto themſelves, diſhonour unto their <hi>City,</hi> and deſtruction to their <hi>Trades,</hi> (which cannot be recovered again but by a ſetled <hi>peace</hi>) the <hi>Scots</hi> may gueſſe how little countenance or aſſiſtance they are like to obtain at their hands, except they ſo declare for his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> as that they may receive aſſurance of his ſpeedy reſtitution; without which, they are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally convinced, there can be no hope of <hi>Peace</hi> unto the <hi>Nation.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:114752:16"/>
               <p>Laſtly, if it ſhould ſo happen, that the <hi>Scots</hi> play falſe with his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and drive both him and the <hi>Independent party to extremity,</hi> it is probable they may unite upon <hi>reaſonable</hi> conſiderations, and mutuall <hi>compliance</hi> betwixt both their <hi>intereſts:</hi> and then that <hi>Party</hi> being for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified by an addition of the <hi>Royall,</hi> which (whereſoever it fides) brings in the <hi>affections</hi> of the whole Kingdom, it is very poſſible, the <hi>Scots</hi> may not onely be defeated in the hopes of that large Dominion, and thoſe golden <hi>mountains</hi> which they promiſed unto themſelves here, by an eſtabliſhment of <hi>Presbytery;</hi> but alſo be forced to pack home again, without ſo much as one ſuperſtitious croſſe, to requite them for the pains they have taken in the work of <hi>Reformation;</hi> and (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) draw revenge upon themſelves, for all thoſe affronts and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries done unto his <hi>Majesty</hi> and the people of <hi>England,</hi> and renew the old <hi>antipathy</hi> with perpetuall <hi>enmity</hi> betwixt the <hi>Nations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From all which, give me leave to ſum up this <hi>Concluſion</hi> in a word, that the <hi>Scots</hi> have no way to reſtore an <hi>Intereſt</hi> again in this <hi>Nation,</hi> but by waving the corrupt <hi>intereſt</hi> of <hi>Presbytery,</hi> and engaging abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely for the <hi>Royall Intereſt</hi> of his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> as the onely means con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to the weal and benefit of both Kingdoms.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Seneca in Thyeſte.</bibl>
                  <l>Nemo confidat nimiùm ſecundis;</l>
                  <l>Nemo deſperet meliorum lapſis.</l>
                  <l>Miſcet haec illis, prohibetque <hi>Clotho</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Stare <hi>fortunam.</hi>—</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
